So as a fashion designer,
إذن كمصممة أزياء،
I've always tended to think of materials
دائما ما أميل إلى التفكير في مواد
something like this,
شيء مثل هذا،
or this,
أو هذا،
or maybe this.
أو ربما هذا.
But then I met a biologist,
ولكن بعد ذلك التقيت أحيائيا،
and now I think of materials like this --
والآن أفكر في مواد مثل هذه --
green tea, sugar,
شاي أخضر، سكر،
a few microbes and a little time.
بضعة ميكروبات وبعض الوقت.
I'm essentially using a kombucha recipe,
أستخدم أساسا وصفة الكومبوشا،
which is a symbiotic mix
والتي هي خليط تكافلي
of bacteria, yeasts and other micro-organisms,
من الباكتيريا، والخمائر وكائنات مجهرية أخرى،
which spin cellulose
والتي تحول السليلوز
in a fermentation process.
في عملية تخمير.
Over time, these tiny threads
مع مرور الوقت، هذه الخيوط الدقيقة
form in the liquid into layers
تشكل من السائل طبقات
and produce a mat on the surface.
وتنتج حصيرة على السطح.
So we start by brewing the tea.
وبالتالي نبدأ بتخمير الشاي.
I brew up to about 30 liters of tea at a time,
أخمر 30 لترا من الشاي تقريبا في كل مرة،
and then while it's still hot, add a couple of kilos of sugar.
ثم وحين لا يزال ساخنا، أضيف بضع كيلوات من السكر.
We stir this in until it's completely dissolved
نمزج هذا حتى يتحلل بالكامل
and then pour it into a growth bath.
وثم نصبه في حوض النمو.
We need to check that the temperature
يجب علينا أن نتحقق أن الحراراة
has cooled to below 30 degrees C.
قد بردت إلى ما تحت 30 درجة مئوية.
And then we're ready to add the living organism.
وثم نكون مستعدين لإضافة الكائن الحي.
And along with that, some acetic acid.
وبالإضافة إلى ذلك، بعضا من حمض الخليك.
And once you get this process going,
وبمجرد أن تجعل العملية تستمر،
you can actually recycle
يمكن في الواقع إعادة تدوير
your previous fermented liquid.
السائل المخمر السابق.
We need to maintain an optimum temperature for the growth.
نحتاج إلى المحافظة على درجة حرارة مثالية من أجل النمو.
And I use a heat mat to sit the bath on
وأستخدم سجادة حرارية لوضع الحوض عليها
and a thermostat to regulate it.
وجهاز تنظيم حرارة لضبطه.
And actually, in hot weather, I can just grow it outside.
وفي الواقع، في جو حار، يمكن فقط أن أزرعه خارجا.
So this is my mini fabric farm.
إذن هذه مزرعتي المصغرة للقماش.
After about three days,
بعد حوالي ثلاثة أيام،
the bubbles will appear on the surface of the liquid.
ستظهر الفقاعات على سطح السائل.
So this is telling us that the fermentation is in full swing.
وهذا يخبرنا أن التخمير قد بلغ أوجه.
And the bacteria are feeding
والبكتيريا تتغذى
on the sugar nutrients in the liquid.
على مغذيات السكر في السائل.
So they're spinning these tiny nano fibers
وبالتالي تقوم بغزل ألياف النانو الدقيقة هذه
of pure cellulose.
من السليلوز النقي.
And they're sticking together, forming layers
وهي تلتصق ببعضها، مشكلة طبقات
and giving us a sheet on the surface.
وتعطينا غطاء على السطح.
After about two to three weeks,
وبعد حوالي أسبوعين أو ثلاثة،
we're looking at something which is about an inch in thickness.
نرى شيئا تقارب سماكته إنشا.
So the bath on the left is after five days,
وهكذا الحوض على اليسار هو بعد خمسة أيام،
and on the right, after 10.
وعلى اليمين، بعد 10.
And this is a static culture.
وهذه زراعة ثابتة.
You don't have to do anything to it;
لا يتوجب علينا القيام بأي شيء؛
you just literally watch it grow.
فقط نشاهدها تنمو حرفيا.
It doesn't need light.
لا تحتاج ضوء.
And when it's ready to harvest, you take it out of the bath
وحين تكون جاهزة للحصاد، تخرجها من الحوض
and you wash it in cold, soapy water.
وتغسلها بماء بارد صابوني.
At this point, it's really heavy.
وفي هذه النقطة، تكون ثقيلة بالفعل.
It's over 90 percent water,
إنها أكثر من 90 في المئة مياه،
so we need to let that evaporate.
لذلك نحتاج إلى ترك ذلك يتبخر.
So I spread it out onto a wooden sheet.
وهكذا ننشرها على صفيحة خشبية.
Again, you can do that outside
ومرة أخرى، يمكن القيام بهذا خارجا
and just let it dry in the air.
وتتركها تنشف فقط في الهواء.
And as it's drying, it's compressing,
وخلال ذلك، تنضغط،
so what you're left with, depending on the recipe,
وبالتالي ما يتبقى لنا، بالاعتماد على الوصفة،
is something that's either
هو شيء إما
like a really light-weight, transparent paper,
مثل ورق شفاف خفيف في الوزن للغاية،
or something which is much more like a flexible vegetable leather.
أو شيء يشبه أكثر جلدا نباتيا مرنا.
And then you can either cut that out
ومن ثم يمكننا إما أن نقطع ذلك
and sew it conventionally,
ونخيطه تقليديا،
or you can use the wet material
أو يمكن أن نستخدم المادة المبتلة
to form it around a three-dimensional shape.
لتشكيلها حول شكل ثلاثي الأبعاد.
And as it evaporates,
وأثناء تبخره،
it will knit itself together, forming seams.
سوف ينسج نفسه بنفسه، مكونا لحامات.
So the color in this jacket is coming purely from green tea.
وبالتالي فإن اللون في هذه السترة يأتي من الشاي الأخضر بشكل مجرد.
I guess it also looks a little bit like human skin,
أفترض أنها تشبه قليلا الجلد البشري،
which intrigues me.
الشيء الذي يأسرني.
Since it's organic,
بما أنه عضوي،
I'm really keen to try and minimize the addition of any chemicals.
أنا في غاية التحمس لتجريب وتقليص إضافة أي من المواد الكيماوية.
I can make it change color without using dye
أستطيع جعله يغيراللون من دون استعمال الصباغة
by a process of iron oxidation.
من خلال عملية أكسدة الحديد.
Using fruit and vegetable staining,
باستخدام بقع الفواكه والخضار،
create organic patterning.
أنتج زخرفة عضوية.
And using indigo,
وباستخدام النيلي،
make it anti-microbial.
أجعله مضادا للميكروبات.
And in fact, cotton
وفي الواقع، القطن
would take up to 18 dips in indigo
قد يستغرق ما يصل إلى 18 غمسة في النيلي
to achieve a color this dark.
ليحصل على لون بهذه الدكانة.
And because of the super-absorbency of this kind of cellulose,
وبسبب الإمتصاصية الفائقة لهذا النوع من السليلوز،
it just takes one, and a really short one at that.
يحتاج فقط إلى مرة واحدة، مرة واحدة قصيرة جدا للقيام بذلك.
What I can't yet do is make it water-resistant.
ما لا أستطيع بعد القيام به هو جعله مقاوما للمياه.
So if I was to walk outside in the rain
إن كان علي المشي خارجا تحت المطر
wearing this dress today,
مرتدية هذه الملابس اليوم،
I would immediately start to absorb
سأبدأ مباشرة في امتصاص
huge amounts of water.
كميات هائلة من الماء.
The dress would get really heavy,
فيصبح اللباس في غاية الثقل،
and eventually the seams would probably fall apart --
وفي نهاية المطاف قد تتفكك اللحامات --
leaving me feeling rather naked.
تاركة إياي عارية في الواقع.
Possibly a good performance piece,
ربما أداء مسرحي جيد،
but definitely not ideal for everyday wear.
لكن بالتأكيد غير مثالي كلباس يومي.
What I'm looking for
ما أبحث عنه
is a way to give the material
هو طريقة لأضفي على المواد
the qualities that I need.
الصفات التي أريد.
So what I want to do is say to a future bug,
لذا ما أريده هو أن أقول لحشرة مستقبلا،
"Spin me a thread.
"اغزلي لي خيطا.
Align it in this direction.
قومي بمراصاته في هذا الإتجاه.
Make it hydrophobic.
اجعليه مقاوما للمياه.
And while you're at it,
وأنت تقومين بذلك،
just form it around this 3D shape."
فقط كونيه حول هذا الشكل الثلاثي الأبعاد."
Bacterial cellulose is actually already being used for wound healing,
السليلوز البكتيري يستخدم في الواققع في شفاء الجروح،
and possibly in the future
وربما في المستقبل
for biocompatible blood vessels,
في أوعية دموية متوافقة حيويا،
possibly even replacement bone tissue.
ربما تعويض النسيج العظمي حتى.
But with synthetic biology,
لكن مع الأحياء الإصطناعية،
we can actually imagine engineering this bacterium
يمكننا في الواقع تخيل تصميم هذا الجرثوم
to produce something
لإنتاج شيء
that gives us the quality,
يعطينا جودة،
quantity and shape
وكمية وشكل
of material that we desire.
المادة التي نريد.
Obviously, as a designer, that's really exciting
بالتأكيد ذلك في غاية الإثارة لي كمصممة.
because then I start to think, wow,
لأنني آنذاك أبدأ في التفكير، واو،
we could actually imagine
نستطيع فعلا تخيل
growing consumable products.
زراعة منتجات إستهلاكية.
What excites me about using microbes
الذي يثيرني حول استخدام الميكروبات
is their efficiency.
هو كفاءتها.
So we only grow what we need.
وبالتالي نزرع فقط ما نحتاجه.
There's no waste.
ليس هناك أي هدر.
And in fact, we could make it from a waste stream --
وفي الحقيقة، نستطيع إنتاجه من سيل نفايات --
so for example,
على سبيل المثال،
a waste sugar stream
تدفق السكر المبدد
from a food processing plant.
من مصنع معالجة الأغذية.
Finally, at the end of use, we could biodegrade it naturally
أخيرا، وبعد الإستعمال، نستطيع أن نحلله طبيعيا
along with your vegetable peelings.
جنبا إلى جنب مع قشور الخضر.
What I'm not suggesting is that microbial cellulose
ما لا أقترحه هو أن السليلوز الميكروبي
is going to be a replacement
سيكون تعويضا
for cotton, leather or other textile materials.
للقطن أوالجلد أو مواد نسيجية أخرى.
But I do think it could be quite a smart and sustainable addition
لكنني أعتقد أنه سيكون إضافة ذكية ومستدامة جيدة
to our increasingly precious natural resources.
لمواردنا الطبيعية المتزايدة النفاسة.
Ultimately, maybe it won't even be fashion
وفي النهاية، قد لا يكون حتى موضة
where we see these microbes have their impact.
أن نرى هذه الميكروبات تؤثر.
We could, for example, imagine
نستطيع، مثلا، تخيل
growing a lamp, a chair,
زراعة مصباح، كرسي،
a car or maybe even a house.
سيارة أو ربما حتى منزل.
So I guess what my question to you is:
لذلك أفترض أن سؤالي لكم هو:
in the future, what would you choose to grow?
في المستقبل، ما الذي ستختارون زراعته؟
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Suzanne, just a curiosity,
برونو جوساني: سوزان، فقط بعجالة،
what you're wearing is not random. (Suzanne Lee: No.)
ما تلبسينه ليس عشوائيا. (سوزان لي: لا.)
This is one of the jackets you grew?
هذه إحدى السترات التي تزرعينها؟
SL: Yes, it is.
س.ل: نعم، إنها كذلك.
It's probably -- part of the project's still in process
إنها على الأرجح -- جزء من المشروع لا يزال قيد الإنجاز،
because this one
لأن هذه
is actually biodegrading in front of your eyes.
هي في الواقع تتحلل أمام أعينكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's absorbing my sweat, and it's feeding on it.
إنها تمتص عرقي، وتتغذى عليه.
BG: Okay, so we'll let you go and save it, and rescue it.
ب.ج: حسنا، سندعك تذهبين وتحفظيها وتنقذيها.
Suzanne Lee. (SL: Thank you.)
سوزان لي. (س.ل: شكرا لكم.)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)